<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="MetaDataStyleSheet-NABBS_Dataset_1966-2016_v2016_0.xsl"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Keith L. Pardieck</origin>
        <origin>David J. Ziolkowski, Jr.</origin>
        <origin>Michael Lutmerding</origin>
        <origin>Kate Campbell</origin>
        <origin>Marie-Anne R. Hudson</origin>
        <pubdate>04252017</pubdate>
        <title>North American Breeding Bird Survey Dataset 1966 - 2016, version 2016.0</title>
        <geoform>Electronic text files.</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Laurel, MD</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>doi:10.5066/F7W0944J</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>
	  	   The 1966-2016 North American Breeding Bird Survey dataset contains avian point count data for more than 700 North American bird taxa (species, races, and unidentified species groupings).  These data are collected annually during the breeding season, primarily June, along thousands of randomly established roadside survey routes in the United States and Canada. Routes are roughly 24.5 miles (39.2 km) long with counting locations placed at approximately half-mile (800-m) intervals, for a total of 50 stops. At each stop, a person highly skilled in avian identification conducts a 3-minute point count, recording every bird seen within a quarter-mile (400-m) radius and every bird heard.  Surveys begin 30 minutes before local sunrise and take approximately 5 hours to complete.  A route is sampled once per year, with the total number of routes sampled per year growing over time; just over 500 routes were sampled in 1966, while in recent decades approximately 3000 routes have been sampled annually.  In addition to avian count data, this dataset also contains survey date, survey start and end times, start and end weather conditions, a unique observer identification number, route identification information, route location information including geographic coordinates of route start point, and an indicator of sample quality.  
	  </abstract>
      <purpose>
	       The North American Breeding Bird Survey provides scientifically credible measures of the status and trends of North American bird populations at continental and regional scales to inform biologically sound conservation and management actions.  A key feature of the BBS that distinguishes it from most other avian monitoring programs is its scientifically rigorous yet straight-forward sampling protocol, the breadth of its geographical coverage and its temporal longevity. It is unique in providing annual information on population abundance and trends across most of the breeding ranges of hundreds of species simultaneously.  Because population change may differ among regions, no other survey is as useful as the BBS for documenting the population status of relatively common and widespread species at a near continental scale. 
		   The primary functions of the BBS data are to measure avian population change to help identify species priorities for conservation, and to provide annual avian count data for model-based conservation planning.  Yet these data have many potential uses, and researchers continue to find new applications of these data each year to address emerging research and management objectives. 
		   Today the BBS data set provides the foundation for non-game, landbird conservation in North America. Each year long-term population trends are calculated for more than 400 species recorded on BBS routes. These trends inform researchers and wildlife managers of significant changes in bird population levels and are utilized, along with other indicators, by the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, Canadian Wildlife Service, state wildlife agencies, and Partners in Flight to establish national and regional avian conservation priorities. 
	  </purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>1966</begdate>
          <enddate>2016</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>Annually</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>All U.S. states except Hawaii, as well as, all Canadian provinces and territories.</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-168.48632812187</westbc>
        <eastbc>-50.712890626566</eastbc>
        <northbc>72.006023198434</northbc>
        <southbc>22.390309372237</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Ecosystems, Status and Trends</themekt>
        <themekey>biodiversity</themekey>
        <themekey>population trends</themekey>
        <themekey>avian point counts</themekey>
        <themekey>relative abundance</themekey>
        <themekey>population distribution</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
		<placekt>Geographic Names Information System (GNIS)</placekt>
        <placekey>North America</placekey>
        <placekey>United States of America</placekey>
        <placekey>Canada</placekey>
        <placekey>United States</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
<taxonomy>
      <keywtax>
        <taxonkt>USGS Biocomplexity Thesaurus</taxonkt>
        <taxonkey>Birds</taxonkey>
      </keywtax>
      <taxonsys>
        <classsys>
          <classcit>
            <citeinfo>
              <origin>American Ornithologists' Union</origin>
              <pubdate>1998</pubdate>
              <title>Check-list of North American Birds, 7th ed.</title>
              <geoform>Electronic text files.</geoform>
              <pubinfo>
                <pubplace>Washington, D.C.</pubplace>
                <publish>American Ornithologists' Union</publish>
              </pubinfo>
              <onlink>http://americanornithology.org/content/aou-checklist-north-and-middle-american-birds-7th-edition-and-supplements</onlink>
            </citeinfo>
          </classcit>
        </classsys>
        <classsys>
          <classcit>
            <citeinfo>
              <origin>R.T. Chesser, K.J. Burns, C. Cicero, J.L. Dunn, A.W. Kratter, I.J. Lovette, P.C. Rasmussen, J. V. Remsen, Jr., J.D. Rising, D.F. Stotz, and K. Winker</origin>
              <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
              <title>FIFTY-SEVENTH SUPPLEMENT TO THE AMERICAN ORNITHOLOGISTS' UNION Check-list of North American Birds</title>
              <geoform>Electronic text files.</geoform>
              <pubinfo>
                <pubplace>Unknown</pubplace>
                <publish>The Auk: Ornithological Advances 133:544-560</publish>
              </pubinfo>
              <onlink>http://www.americanornithologypubs.org/doi/full/10.1642/AUK-16-77.1</onlink>
            </citeinfo>
          </classcit>
        </classsys>
        <ider>
          <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
              <cntper>Dave Ziolkowski, Jr.</cntper>
              <cntorg>USGS Patuxent Wildlife Research Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
              <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
              <address>12100 Beech Forest Road</address>
              <city>Laurel</city>
              <state>MD</state>
              <postal>20708</postal>
              <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>301-497-5753</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>dziolkowski@usgs.gov</cntemail>
          </cntinfo>
        </ider>
        <taxonpro>expert advice;identification keys</taxonpro>
        <taxoncom>Data are collected by individuals who are highly skilled in aural and visual identification of wild birds.  The data are then reviewed by area experts for accuracy, with appropriate corrections made, as necessary, in consultation with observer, reference works and local area experts.</taxoncom>
      </taxonsys>
      <taxongen>
	       The majority of birds were identified to level of species in the data.  In some cases individuals are identified to race or an unidentified species group for data management purposes.  See SpeciesList.txt for list of species and taxa groups. 
		   Numerous changes in the taxonomy of North American birds have occurred since 1966, and are described in the sixth and seventh editions of the American Ornithologists' Union Check-list of North American Birds and subsequent supplements.  The BBS attempts to maintain a database that reflects these taxonomic and nomenclatural changes.  However, in some cases BBS data management needs dictate deviation from the AOU check-list. For example, when two or more species have been lumped into a single species, the BBS usually maintains the former species as separate taxonomic entities within the database.  Thus lumping and re-splitting of some species during the history of the BBS has not affected how the data have been treated.  When a species is split into two or more species, the treatment of existing data within the database is dependent on the population distributions of the new species.  If their population distributions are completely disjunct, then assignment of existing data within the database to the new species poses no problems.  If the new species' population distributions overlap, then it may not be possible to assign existing data to the appropriate species group, and may dictate the formation of an indeterminate taxa group composed of the two or more overlapping species. 
		   The BBS uses a 5-digit species identification code to uniquely identify species within the database.  While originally derived from American Ornithologists' Union's species identification numbers (Which is why they are referred to as "AOU numbers" or "AOU" in some data tables.), and then later followed the numbering system of Sibley and Monroe (1990), the BBS no longer attempts to maintain concordance with either species numbering system. They are simply 5-digit species identification codes used to manage data within the BBS database. 
		   Sibley, C.G., and B.L. Monroe, Jr.  1990.  Distribution and taxonomy of birds of the world.  Yale University Press, New Haven, CT.  1111p.  
	  </taxongen>
      <taxoncl>
        <taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
        <taxonrv>Animalia</taxonrv>
        <taxoncl>
          <taxonrn>Subkingdom</taxonrn>
          <taxonrv>Bilateria</taxonrv>
          <taxoncl>
            <taxonrn>Infrakingdom</taxonrn>
            <taxonrv>Deuterostomia</taxonrv>
            <taxoncl>
              <taxonrn>Phylum</taxonrn>
              <taxonrv>Chordata</taxonrv>
              <taxoncl>
                <taxonrn>Subphylum</taxonrn>
                <taxonrv>Vertebrata</taxonrv>
                <taxoncl>
                  <taxonrn>Infraphylum</taxonrn>
                  <taxonrv>Gnathostomata</taxonrv>
                  <taxoncl>
                    <taxonrn>Superclass</taxonrn>
                    <taxonrv>Tetrapoda</taxonrv>
                    <taxoncl>
                      <taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
                      <taxonrv>Aves</taxonrv>
                      <common>Birds</common>
                      <common>oiseaux</common>
                    </taxoncl>
                  </taxoncl>
                </taxoncl>
              </taxoncl>
            </taxoncl>
          </taxoncl>
        </taxoncl>
      </taxoncl>
    </taxonomy>
    <accconst>none</accconst>
    <useconst>
		This database, identified as the North American Breeding Bird Survey Dataset, has been approved for release and publication by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) and the Canadian Wildlife Service of Environment and Climate Change Canada (ECCC). Although this database has been subjected to rigorous review and is substantially complete, the USGS and ECCC reserve the right to revise the data pursuant to further analysis and review. 
		Furthermore, it is released on the condition that the USGS, the U.S. Government, the ECCC, and the Canadian Government may not be held liable for any damages resulting from its authorized or unauthorized use.
		Users of these BBS data are obligated to formally recognize their use of the program's data in publications, presentations and other outlets. Additionally, all work using these data should acknowledge the thousands of U.S. and Canadian participants who annually perform and coordinate the survey.
		If a publication is based solely on the analysis of BBS data, we recommend that you involve National BBS staff with the writing and/or review of the manuscript.
		It is in the best interest for the continued success of the BBS that authors submit a reprint or pdf of their work featuring BBS data to the National BBS staff for inclusion in the program's bibliography.  Thank you for supporting the BBS program and we look forward to learning of your work.
    </useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Keith L. Pardieck or Dave Ziolkowski, Jr.</cntper>
          <cntorg>USGS Patuxent Wildlife Research Center</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>12100 Beech Forest Road</address>
          <city>Laurel</city>
          <state>MD</state>
          <postal>20708-4038</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>301-497-5843</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>kpardieck@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>U.S. Geological Survey Patuxent Wildlife Research Center; Environment Canada, Canadian Wildlife Service</datacred>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>Data set has been subjected to multiple computerized quality assurance and quality control routines that evaluate data for computational, 
value range, and species range errors.  Flags raised during QAQC process are manually reviewed by professional staff for accuracy, with appropriate 
corrections made in consultation with observer, reference works and local area experts, as necessary.  Upon completion of data processing, observers 
are asked to complete one final manual data review to ensure accuracy.</logic>
    <complete>
		 Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the entire metadata record carefully for additional details.  BBS Data are housed in MS-SQL 2014 database.  Numerous scripts and SQL queries, developed by USGS staff (BBSRetrievalData_V1.0), are used to repackage data into the flatfiles for data set release. 
		 1) BBS data provide an index of population abundance, not a complete count of birds at a stop or on a route.  Only those birds visible or audible to the observer during the 3-minute point count period are identified to species, or appropriate BBS taxa group, and enumerated.  Weather, habitat, bird activity levels, time of day, ambient noise, human abilities, and much more may affect detection rates of birds.  The BBS controls for many of these factors by utilizing a rigorous and standardized sampling protocol.  Nevertheless, incorporation of covariates like observer effects have been shown to play an important role in mitigating bias when analyzing BBS data.  Other important factors include first-time observer effect and sample density. 
		 Faanes, C. A. and D. Bystrak. 1981. The role of observer bias in the North American Breeding Bird Survey. Pages 353-359 in C. John Ralph and J. Michael Scott Estimating Numbers of Terrestrial Birds.  Studies in Avian Biology 6., 630 pp. http://sora.unm.edu/node/49 
		 Kendall, W. L., B. G. Peterjohn, and J. R. Sauer. 1996. First-time observer effects in the North American Breeding Bird Survey. Auk 113(4):823-829. http://sora.unm.edu/node/25734 
		 Link, W. A. and J. R. Sauer. 1997. Estimation of population trajectories from count data. Biometrics 53(2):488-497. http://www.jstor.org/stable/info/2533952 
		 Sauer, J. R., W. A. Link, and J. A. Royle. 2004. Estimating population trends with a linear model: technical comments. Condor 106(2):435-440. <![CDATA[http://www.bioone.org/perlserv/?request=get-abstract&doi=10.1650/7431]]> 
		 Sauer, J. R. and W. A. Link. 2011. Analysis of the North American Breeding Bird Survey using hierarchical models. Auk 128(1):87-98. http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1525/auk.2010.09220 
		 2) Breeding bird species.  Breeding birds are defined as any bird, except dependent young, detected within that species' known local breeding population range and within the accepted breeding season for the region where detected.  No attempt is made to distinguish between paired and unpaired individuals.  Migrant (a.k.a., migrant, vagrant or nonbreeding) species information has not been consistently collected or stored for most of the survey's history due to survey's focus on breeding species.  Steps were taken in 2001 to preserve "Migrant" information prospectively; "Migrant" data can be more accurately identified as "NOT-breeder" since the migrant data set contains all data not fitting into the "Breeding" category regardless of data quality. 
		 3) Sample density (i.e., route density) varies across time and space.  The survey was initiated in different years in different parts of its range.  The BBS began in 1966 with about 500 routes sampled in the United States east of the Mississippi River and in Quebec and the maritime provinces of Canada.  In 1967, the BBS expanded to the central United States, with a few routes in Ontario and Manitoba.  By 1968 approximately 1200 routes were established and being sampled across the contiguous United States and southern half of all Canadian provinces, with only 2-3 routes being sampled in Alaska until the 1980s.  Today there are around 5000 active routes of which approximately 3000 have been sampled annually since the mid-1990s.  However, the same ~3000 routes are not necessarily sampled each year due to variety of reasons, including: poor weather conditions, safety concerns, and participant availability (e.g., illness). 
		 Many patterns occur in geographic coverage of the BBS.  Some patterns occur as a consequence of logistics.  BBS routes near human population centers tend to be consistently surveyed but remote routes are not surveyed every year, which causes regional variation in the efficiency of the survey (Robbins et al. 1986).  Although all States and Provinces vary in coverage over time, some consistent regional patterns occur in BBS coverage.  Route density varies geographically with regions in the northeast and southeast generally having higher route densities than most western and midwestern regions.  For example, Maryland has approximately 14 routes per degree block, Alabama and Georgia have about 6 routes per degree block, and Nevada and Utah have about 2 routes per degree block.  In Canada, routes are largely restricted to the southern half of the country; a pattern further reflected within individual provinces and territories. 
		 Lawler, J. J., and R. J. O'Connor. 2004. How well do consistently monitored Breeding Bird Survey routes represent the environments of the conterminous United States? Condor 106:801-814. 
		 Robbins, C.S., D.A. Bystrak, and P.H. Geissler.  1986.  The Breeding Bird Survey:  its first fifteen years, 1965-1979.  USDOI, Fish and Wildlife Service resource publication 157.  Washington, D.C. 
		 4) While sample locations (i.e., routes) are established using a stratified random process, they are constrained to roadsides except for a handful of water routes in Alaska and Alabama.  This restricted sampling frame has raised questions regarding the influence of roadside bias.  There are three primary concerns: 
		 A) habitats along roads may not be representative of habitats in the landscape due to, for example, increased disturbance along roads or placement of roads; 
		 B) counts may not be representative for some species due to differential attraction to, or avoidance of, roadside habitats; 
		 C) counts along roads thru time may not be representative due to differing rates of habitat change on roads versus off roads. 
		 Habitat representation has been fairly well examined in the literature (Bart et al. 1995; Keller and Scallan 1999; Neimuth et al. 2007) with the most extensive study to date (Veech et al. 2012) finding that for most of the 15 NLCD land cover types examined, the habiats within 400m of BBS routes are similar to habitats within 10,000m. Notable exceptions included open water habitat which was underrepresented near routes (1.2% vs. 3.1%) and an over representation of developed open space near routes (3.8% vs. 1.1%).  Nevertheless, differences in local habitat quality or roadside attraction/avoidance effects may influence species abundance on roadside counts (Wellicome et al. 2014). 
		 Bart, J., M. Hofschen, and B. G. Peterjohn. 1995. Reliability of the Breeding Bird Survey: Effects of restricting surveys to roads. Auk 112:758-761. 
		 Keller, C. M. E., and J. T. Scallan. 1999. Potential roadside biases due to habitat changes along breeding bird survey routes. Condor 101:50-57. 
		 Niemuth, N. D., A. L. Dahl, M. E. Estey, and C. R. Loesch. 2007. Representation of landcover along Breeding Bird Survey routes in the Northern Plains. Journal of Wildlife Management 71:2258-2265. 
		 Veech, J. A., M. F. Small, and J. T. Baccus. 2012. Representativeness of Land Cover Composition along Routes of the North American Breeding Bird Survey. Auk 129(2):259-267. (http://www.bioone.org/doi/abs/10.1525/auk.2012.11242) (http://dx.doi.org/10.1525/auk.2012.11242) 
		 Wellicome, T. I., K. J. Kardynal, R. J. Franken, and C. S. Gillies. 2014. Off-road sampling reveals a different grassland bird community than roadside sampling: implications for survey design and estimates to guide conservation. Avian Conservation and Ecology 9(1): 4. http://dx.doi.org/10.5751/ACE-00624-090104 
		 5) Each route-year sample unit is grouped into one of two broad data quality categories as indicated in the "RunType" field found in the "Weather.zip" file.  
		Runtype = 1 indicates that the associated data meet BBS data quality criteria and are suitable for use in the standard USGS trend and relative abundance analyses; 
		Runtype = 0 indicates that the data were not collected according to prescribed methods and/or were collected during unsuitable weather conditions.  Data with Runtype code equal to 0 are not used in standard USGS trend or relative abundance analyses. 
	</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>Field</methtype>
        <methdesc>Sample locations are established using a stratified random process within a state/province/territory where the stratification unit is 1-degree block of latitude-longitude; site selection is constrained by availability of suitable roads to conduct counts.  Sample routes consist of 50 roadside sample locations spaced at approximately 800-meter intervals, as road and safety conditions allow.  A 3-minute point count is conducted at each stop by one person, highly skilled in avian identification, who identifies and records all birds detected.  Each route starts 30 minutes before local sunrise and takes approximately 5 hours to complete.</methdesc>
        <methcite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>USGS and CWS</origin>
            <pubdate>1998</pubdate>
            <title>Instructions for Conducting the North American Breeding Bird Survey</title>
            <geoform>Document</geoform>
            <onlink>www.pwrc.usgs.gov/bbs/participate/instructions.html</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </methcite>
      </method>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>
			Data submitted to BBS office via web or U.S. Postal Service by observer.  If submitted via web, observer then mails hard copies of completed data forms to BBS office for quality assurance and archiving purposes.  Data submitted via US Postal Service are either input using optical character recognition technology or via the web by BBS staff.  Once electronically submitted, the data are subjected to a battery of computerized quality assurance and quality control routines to identify potentially incorrect, out of range, and incomplete data.  These data flags are manually reviewed by BBS staff who use expert knowledge, published references, original data sheets, local experts, and communication with observers and state coordinators to resolve the identified data flags. Once data flags are resolved, the data are released to observer for one final review for accuracy.  
Data are subjected to one final end-of-year review and route data quality is assessed.  Data are categorized into two groups: 
			1) Data that meet all BBS data criteria and are acceptable for population trend analysis (runtype = 1), and 
			2) Data that fail to meet BBS data criteria and are not acceptable for use in population trend analysis (runtype = 0).  
			Approximately 10% of the data are not suitable for population trend analysis.
		</procdesc>
        <procdate>20150306</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Point</direct>
  </spdoinfo>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>Data fields and definitions are described in NABBS_DataFieldDefinitions_1996-2016 file included.  Or see ReadMe file included.</eaover>
      <eadetcit>ftp://ftpext.usgs.gov/pub/er/md/laurel/BBS/DataFiles/NABBS_DataFieldDefinitions_1996-2016.xml</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Keith Pardieck or Dave Ziolkowski, Jr.</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>12100 Beech Forest Road</address>
          <city>Laurel</city>
          <state>MD</state>
          <postal>20708-4038</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>301-497-5843</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>kpardieck@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>This database, identified as the North American Breeding Bird Survey Dataset, has been approved for release and publication by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) and the Canadian Wildlife Service of Environment Canada (EC). Although this database has been subjected to rigorous review and is substantially complete, the USGS and EC reserve the right to revise the data pursuant to further analysis and review.  Furthermore, it is released on the condition that the USGS, the U.S. Government, the EC, and the Canadian Government may not be held liable for any damages resulting from its authorized or unauthorized use.</distliab>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160218</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Keith Pardieck</cntper>
          <cntorg>USGS Patuxent Wildlife Research Center</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Wildlife Biologist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>12100 Beech Forest Road</address>
          <city>Laurel</city>
          <state>MD</state>
          <postal>20708-4038</postal>
          <country>U.S.A.</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>301-497-5843</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>kpardieck@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>

